Well, wait, it's long.
嗯，等等，这个挺长的。
Okay, it looks like the transcription is turned off for the meeting organizer by organizing policy.
好吧，根据组织政策，会议组织者的转录功能似乎已经关闭了。
Okay, I suppose the recording has no problem.
好吧，我想这录音没问题。
Previously, I can see the transcript to guarantee the recording is on, but today I cannot.
之前我可以通过查看转录本来确认录音是开启的，但今天却做不到这一点了。
So I suppose the recording is on and it can record my voice.
因此我猜录音设备已经开启，能够录下我的声音。
But there's no transcript.
但是没有文字记录，请见谅。
Stop.
停止
Turn on.
打开（更自然的表达）
Do it here.
在这里执行。
Start.
开始。
Okay, I suppose the recording is fine, okay?
好吧，我觉得录音应该没问题，对吧？
Because the mic here is on, although I cannot see the transcript.
因为这里的麦克风是开着的，虽然我看不到文稿。
Okay, anyway, the recording isn't on.
好吧，不管怎样，录音没开。
Sure.
当然。
Here is start recording.
这里开始录制。
Start recording.
开始录制。
Okay, so we start.
好吧，那我们就开始了。
Okay, last time we talked about the lecture three about cryptography.
好的，上次我们讨论了关于密码学的第三讲。
So we finished part one about the summation encryption.
我们完成了关于求和加密的第一部分，内容如下：
In summation encryption, we have the idea that both the sender and the receiver, they share the same key, K.
在求和加密中，发送者和接收者共享同一个密钥 K，这一概念被提出。
Key K will be used for both encryption and decryption.
密钥 K 将同时用于加密和解密。
And we have the common null encryption algorithm and decryption algorithm.
我们拥有常见的空加密和解密算法。
Just like in this example, we use AES.
就像在这个例子中，我们使用 AES。这个翻译已经比较自然和易懂了。
Well, in this summation encryption, only the key K will be secret.
嗯，在这种求和加密中，只有密钥 K 是保密的。
Others, like the encryption algorithm and decryption algorithm, will know to everyone.
其他，例如加密和解密算法，大家都会知道。
So this model, and we talked about the SIDA CIFR.
因此，我们讨论了这个模型以及 SIDA 的 CIFR。
So SIDA CIFR is easy to be attacked because we can try all possible cases, right?
SIDA CIFR 非常容易受到攻击，因为我们可以尝试所有可能的情况，对吧？
Just like in this example, we can use a brute force attack.
就像这个例子一样，我们可以使用暴力攻击。
The key K can be tested from 1 to 25.
关键字 K 可以从 1 测试到 25。
Then we talk about the one-time path.
我们再讨论一次性路径（使翻译更自然易懂）。
The one-time path is only null, perfect, secrecy scheme.
一次性路径仅能是空值，这是一个完美的保密方案。
However, one-time path is quite difficult to be applied in the reality, in the real world.
然而，在现实中，一次性路径的应用相当困难。
Because one-time path requires the key length.
因为一次性路径需要指定键的长度。
The key length will be the same as your plaintext.
密钥长度将与您的明文长度一致
In part two, we talked about the public key scheme.
在第二部分，我们讨论了公钥方案。这里所说的公钥方案是指...
Particularly, we talked about the RSA algorithm.
尤其是我们讨论了 RSA 算法。
So in this RSA algorithm, we show the mechanism.
在这个 RSA 算法中，我们展示了其工作原理。
Why do we have the RSA algorithm?
我们为什么会有 RSA 算法呢？
From the Euler's theorem, how we can generate the public key and the private key here.
从欧拉定理出发，我们在这里是如何生成公钥和私钥的。
So according to our previous knowledge in the module inverse Euclidean algorithm,
we can derive the public key and private key to make sure that the ED and DNE, the module inverse, mod phi n.
我们可以推导出公钥和私钥，以确保 ED 和 DNE，模逆元，模φn。这样的表述更加自然和易于理解。
So we know what's the meaning for phi n.
我们知道 phi n 的意思是什么
So this is a real example to see how we can, based on the given PQ value, we have the n value.
因此这是一个真实示例，以查看我们如何根据给定的 PQ 值，得到 n 值。这使得翻译更加自然和易于理解。
n is a product of P and Q.
n 是由 P 和 Q 相乘得到的。
And because n is a product of two primes, so phi n equals P minus 1 times Q minus 1.
因为 n 是两个质数的乘积，所以φ(n)等于 P 减 1 与 Q 减 1 的乘积。
Once we know the phi n, and also we know the public key E to be 5 here,
一旦我们知道了 phi n 的值，并且已知这里的公钥 E 为 5，
we are able to calculate the module inverse of E to be D.
我们可以计算出 E 的模逆是 D。
So D is the private key.
因此，D 是私钥。
With public key and private key, we can apply the RSA algorithm to calculate the subtext C from the original message M.
使用公钥和私钥，我们可以通过 RSA 算法从原始消息 M 计算出子文本 C。这样的表述更加自然易懂。
So M to the E mod n is C.
所以 M 到 E 模 n 等于 C。
And from C, we can get back to its original message M to apply C to the D mod n.
从 C 出发，我们可以回到原始消息 M，对 D 模 n 应用 C。这使得翻译更加自然和易于理解。
And also we can see we can use CRT, this theorem, to accelerate our calculation of the big numbers.
我们还可以看到，利用 CRT 定理可以加速大数的计算，这样的表述更为自然易懂。
Their exponential operation mod big number n.
他们的指数运算对大数 n 取模。
So this can allow us to quickly get the result for this mod operation.
这样可以让我们快速得到这个模运算的结果，表达更自然。
In part three, we took about another very important concept.
在第三部分，我们探讨了另一个至关重要的概念。
It is a Diffie-Hellman algorithm.
这是一个迪菲-赫尔曼算法。
So this one will allow two parties to calculate the secret key K.
因此，这将允许双方计算密钥 K，表达更为自然。
So they can share this key K, KKA equals KB, to guarantee that they have the same symmetric key K for the future complications.
因此，他们可以共享这个密钥 K，即 KKA 等于 KB，以确保未来在遇到复杂情况时，他们使用的对称密钥 K 是一致的。
So the security is guaranteed that we took about the discrete log algorithm.
因此，我们讨论了如何确保离散对数算法的安全性。
So in the next lecture, in this exponential operation, just like Alice chooses A, Bob chooses B,
所以在下一节课中，在这个指数运算中，就像爱丽丝选择 A 一样，鲍勃选择 B，
Alice will calculate small x from GA mod P.
爱丽丝将从 GA mod P 中计算出一个小 x 值。
But even this x is sent to anyone else.
即使是这个 x 也会被发送给其他人。
So no one will know the chosen A by Alice.
因此，没有人会知道爱丽丝选了哪个 A。
The reason is because this is a discrete log problem.
原因在于这是一个离散对数问题。
So actually it is very hard.
实际上，这真的很困难。
Without knowing the A, only with the value of x, it is impossible to calculate the small a in this Diffie-Hellman algorithm.
在不知 A 的情况下，仅凭 x 的值，根本无法计算出 Diffie-Hellman 算法中的小 a。
The Diffie-Hellman algorithm will allow two people to get the same symmetric key K to be used in the symmetric encryption.
Diffie-Hellman 算法可以让两个人获得相同的对称密钥 K，该密钥可用于对称加密。这个翻译更加自然和易于理解。
So now we look at part four.
现在让我们看看第四部分。
So part four will provide you some knowledge about the public key cryptography, what's the requirement, and how we can look at their security for the RSA algorithm.
第四部分将为您介绍公钥密码学的基础知识，包括其需求以及如何评估 RSA 算法的安全性。
So for RSA algorithm, its security is guaranteed by the factorization of a big number.
因此，RSA 算法的安全性由一个大数的分解来保证，这一点得到了保障。
To factorize, we say factorization is to factorize n to be the product of P and Q.
因式分解，即把 n 分解成 P 和 Q 的乘积。这样的表述更为自然易懂。
So this process is very difficult, given n to be a very large number, to be like 1024 bits.
因此，这个过程相当复杂，假设 n 是一个非常大的数，例如 1024 位。
If you want to get its corresponding P and Q, that would be very difficult.
如果您想找到它的对应 P 和 Q 值，那将会非常困难。
So suppose n is one of 24 bits.
假设 n 是 24 位中的一个。
What's the size for P and Q?
P 和 Q 的尺寸是多少？
P and Q, the size will be what?
P 和 Q 的大小会是多少？
How many bits for P and Q?
P 和 Q 需要多少位？（更自然、更易理解的翻译）
If we suppose n is 1024 bits.
假定 n 有 1024 位。
Any idea?
任何想法？
If it's 512, should be what?
如果是 512，那应该是哪个？
So P and Q will be similar size to n, right?
所以 P 和 Q 的大小将与 n 相似，没错吧？
Should be similar size.
应该大小相近。
Okay, we look at in the public key cryptography, we have different ways to apply the private key and public key.
好的，在公钥密码学中，我们了解到有多种方法可以用来使用私钥和公钥。
So you can use public key in the encryption, or you can use the private key in the encryption.
您可以选择使用公钥或私钥进行加密。这样的表述更为自然易懂。
So first we look at the first scheme, we use the public key in the encryption.
首先我们来查看第一个方案，加密时使用公钥。
Just like support Bob is the sender and Alice is the receiver.
就像支持一样，Bob 是发送方，Alice 是接收方。
So support Bob wants to send a message n to Alice.
因此，支持 Bob 想给 Alice 发送消息 n。
So this message x.
这条消息是 x。
And well, Bob can use Alice's public key to do the encryption, right, to do the encryption.
嗯，鲍勃可以用爱丽丝的公钥进行加密，对吧？
Then the subtext y will be sent to Alice.
然后将子文本 y 发送给 Alice。 (This is the refined translation, as the initial translation is already natural and understandable.)
So this y is encrypted by using Alice's public key.
因此，这个 y 是通过 Alice 的公钥进行加密的，翻译得更加自然和易懂。
So only Alice has a private key, so other than Alice, no one else can do the decryption.
因此，只有 Alice 拥有私钥，其他人无法进行解密。这样的表述更为自然易懂。
So Alice can use her private key to do the decryption and get back the original message x.
因此，Alice 可以用她的私钥进行解密，恢复原始消息 x。
So this y in the RSA algorithm, we know that the public key is e and n, right?
所以在 RSA 算法中，我们知道公钥是 e 和 n，这个 y 指的是什么？对吧？
And private key is d.
私钥为 d。
So this y equals x to the e mod n.
因此，这个 y 等于 x 的 e 次方对 n 取模。
And to do the decryption, Alice will apply her private key.
为了解密，Alice 将使用她的私钥。这样的表述更加自然易懂。
So to get back x equals the subtext y to the private key d mod n.
因此，要得到 x 等于私钥 d 对 n 取模后的子文本 y。
OK, so this is the encryption and the decryption process.
好的，这就是加密和解密的过程。 （经过润色，使翻译更加自然易懂）
Of course, someone can apply the second case using the private key to do the encryption.
当然，有人可以利用私钥来应用第二种加密方式。
So Bob will use his private key to do the encryption.
因此鲍勃将使用他的私钥进行加密。
So this y equals x to the d mod n, right?
所以这个 y 等于 x 的 d 次方对 n 取模，对吧？
Well, using your private key, you can do decryption.
嗯，用您的私钥，您可以进行解密操作。
But anyone else can use your public key to do the decryption.
但任何人都可以使用您的公钥进行解密，表达更为自然。
Your public key is publicly known by everyone.
您的公钥为公众所知，表述更为自然。
So Alice can use Bob's public key to do the decryption.
因此 Alice 可以使用 Bob 的公钥进行解密。
So Alice can obtain the plaintext by applying y to the e mod n.
因此 Alice 可以通过对 e 模 n 应用 y 来获取明文。
OK, so because, well, you can see this y equals x to the d e mod n.
好吧，所以因为，嗯，你可以看到这个 y 等于 x 的 d 次方除以 n 的余数。
This is x to the e d mod n.
这是 x 的 e 次方除以 n 的余数（更自然地表达）。
So e d, in fact, equals x to the k times 5 plus 1 mod n, right?
事实上，So e d 等于 x 的 k 次方乘以 5 再加 1，然后对 n 取模，对吧？
Because we will choose e d is congruent to 1 mod phi n.
因为我们将选择 e d 与φ n 同余 1，这样表达更为自然易懂。
So according to the Euler's theorem, well, this mod n in the exponent part phi n, this one can be cancelled.
根据欧拉定理，嗯，这个指数部分的模 n 在 n 的欧拉函数中可以约掉，翻译得更加自然易懂。
OK, normally we apply the second scheme to generate the signature.
好的，我们通常采用第二个方案来生成签名。这样的表达更自然、易懂。
Somehow this is not a standard way to generate the signature.
这种生成签名的方法并不符合常规。
But the idea is the same.
但这个想法是相同的。
You will use your private key to generate your signature.
您将使用您的私钥来生成您的签名。（更自然、更易理解的翻译）
And others will use your public key to do the signature verification, right?
其他人会用您的公钥进行签名验证，您觉得对吗？
Because only you have that unique private key.
因为只有你才拥有那个独一无二的私钥。
So others can use your public key to do verification.
以便其他人可以使用您的公钥进行验证，这样更自然易懂。
That message is really from Alice because the receiver is using Alice public key to do the verification.
那条消息确实来自 Alice，因为接收者正在使用 Alice 的公钥进行验证，这一点非常明确。
Well, for the public key crypto systems, well, this can solve two important problems.
好吧，对于公钥加密系统来说，嗯，这可以解决两个关键问题。这样的表述可能更自然、更易于理解。
The concept of public key cryptography evolved from an attempt to solve two of the most difficult problems associated with the symmetric encryption.
公钥密码学的概念起源于尝试解决与对称加密相关的两个最棘手的问题。以下是对该概念的更自然和易于理解的表述：公钥密码学的概念源于尝试解决与对称加密相关的两个最困难的问题。
So that means in symmetric encryption, it is very hard to get key distribution and very hard to generate the digital signatures.
这意味着在对称加密中，密钥分配非常困难，生成数字签名也相当不易。
Well, in the symmetric encryption, both the sender and the receiver, they should have the same key.
在对称加密中，发送方和接收方应使用相同的密钥。
So before they can do encryption, decryption, they should have the same key.
在进行加密和解密操作之前，它们必须使用相同的密钥。
How to get the same key for both sender and receiver?
如何为发送者和接收者获取相同的密钥？
We said this is a key distribution problem, right?
我们说这确实是一个密钥分发问题，您同意吗？
So in fact, it is difficult.
事实上，做这件事挺难的。
Well, in the public key scheme, we can use Diffie-Hellman, DH, this algorithm to provide the key distribution.
好的，在公钥加密方案中，我们可以使用 Diffie-Hellman 算法，即 DH 算法，来实现密钥的分配。
Both sides, they can, after some calculation, they can get the same key for the encryption and decryption.
双方经过计算后，可以得到相同的加密和解密密钥。这样的表述更为自然易懂。
So key distribution means how to have secure communications in general without having to trust.
密钥分发指的是如何在无需信任的情况下实现一般性的安全通信。
So this is a key, the key distribution center with your key, without a trusted third party.
这是一把钥匙，钥匙分配中心保管着您的钥匙，无需依赖第三方。
The second problem is called the digital signature.
第二个问题叫做数字签名。
So this means how to verify that a message comes intact from the claimed sender.
这意味着如何验证一条消息是否完整无缺地来自声称的发送者。
Well, in the public key scheme, we can use the private key of sender to do the encryption to generate the signature.
好的，在公钥加密方案中，我们可以使用发送者的私钥进行加密操作，从而生成签名。
So we can use private key D of the sender to generate signature.
我们可以使用发送者的私钥 D 来生成签名，这样更自然易懂。
OK.
好的。
So the withfield Diffie and Martin Hellman from Stanford University achieved a breakthrough in 1976 by coming up with a method that addressed the key distribution problem.
因此，1976 年，斯坦福大学的惠特菲尔德·迪菲和马丁·赫尔曼提出了一种方法，成功解决了密钥分发难题，实现了重大突破。
So this DH algorithm will allow Alice and Bob to generate the same TK to be used in the symmetric encryption scheme.
因此，这个 DH 算法将允许 Alice 和 Bob 生成相同的密钥 TK，用于对称加密方案，翻译更加自然和易懂。
And RSA algorithm can be used for both purposes.
RSA 算法可以用于这两个目的。
Because RSA algorithm, the original message M can be used as the key.
因为 RSA 算法，原始信息 M 可以用来作为密钥。这样的表述更加自然和易于理解。
M can be used as a key.
M 可以作为键使用。
So this M can be generated by sender and will be decrypted, received by the receiver secretly.
因此，这个 M 可以由发送者生成，接收者将秘密解密并接收。
So this key, this M can be regarded to be the key.
因此，这个 M 可以看作是这把钥匙。
And also in previous slide, well, in the second case, in case B, well, the sender like Bob can use his private key to generate the signature.
在上一张幻灯片中也是如此，嗯，在第二种情况，即情况 B 中，嗯，发送者鲍勃可以使用他的私钥来生成签名。这样的表述更加自然易懂。
So this is a way to generate a signature to be verified by the receiver Alice.
这是一种生成由接收者 Alice 验证的签名的方法。这种方法可以更直观地理解。
OK, we have talked about this one previously for the public key cryptosystem.
好的，我们之前已经就这个公钥密码系统进行过讨论了。
If the sender use the public key of the receiver, like this is A, this is B, A can use B's public key to do the encryption.
如果发送者使用接收者的公钥，例如这是 A，这是 B，A 就可以用 B 的公钥进行加密。这样的表述更加自然易懂。
And send the self-text Y, then only the receiver B can do the decryption.
然后发送自文本 Y，只有接收者 B 才能进行解密。翻译更加自然流畅。
So in this way, we'll guarantee that the secrecy, this property is achieved.
因此，我们将确保实现保密性，这一特性得以保证。
But even this self-text can be obtained by some cryptoanalyst.
即使这种自文本也能被某些密码分析师获得，但翻译起来略显生硬，以下是对其进行润色后的版本：即便这种自述文本也能被某些密码分析师解读出来。
Well, the attacker in the middle, the attacker cannot guess, cannot calculate the private key.
好吧，位于中间的攻击者无法猜测，也无法计算出私钥。这样的表述更为自然易懂。
And not the attacker cannot decrypt the message, cannot get the original message X.
攻击者无法解密信息，无法获取原始信息 X。
So only B with his private key can do the decryption to get the original message X.
只有 B 使用他的私钥才能解密，从而获取原始消息 X。
Well, the second method is to apply the sender's private key to generate, somehow to generate a signature.
嗯，第二种方法是使用发送者的私钥来生成签名，这样生成签名。
So this signature will be verified by receiver B because B will use A's public key to do verification.
因此，这个签名将由接收者 B 进行验证，B 将使用 A 的公钥来进行验证。这样的表述更加自然易懂。
The public key of A to decrypt the message and to verify that the message is really from X, from A.
A 的公钥用于解密消息，并确保消息确实由 X 发出，来自 A。
And we call this the process for authentication.
我们把这个过程称为认证流程。
So authentication means the message is really from someone like from A, right from Alice.
所以说，认证的意思是消息确实来自像 A，也就是 Alice 这样的人。
Well, for receiver, I will use Alice's public key to do the verification.
嗯，对于接收者，我会使用 Alice 的公钥来进行验证。这样表达更自然、易懂。
So that means the message must be sent from Alice.
意思是，这条消息必须由 Alice 发出。
Only Alice has her private key.
只有爱丽丝才有她的私钥。
Of course, you can use both, but you can combine them together.
当然可以同时使用这两个，也可以将它们合并使用，这样更方便。
Well, first, you can use your private key, A's private key, to do the encryption.
好的，首先，您可以使用自己的私钥或 A 的私钥进行加密操作。
That means somehow you can regard this one to be, you generate the signature.
这意味着你可以在某种程度上将其视为，你生成签名。这样表达更为自然和易懂。
Then you use the receiver's public key to do the encryption again.
您再次使用接收者的公钥进行加密，使翻译更加自然易懂。
So this one will, to guarantee the secrecy, the message cannot be decrypted by anyone else, cannot be disclosed, be known by any others.
为了确保保密性，这条信息不能被他人解密，不得泄露，不得让他人得知。
So at the destination part, the receiver can use corresponding decryption algorithm to get back the original message X.
在目的地部分，接收者可以使用相应的解密算法将原始消息 X 还原。
When we apply the public key system, the public key scheme, we can achieve the following three functions.
当我们采用公钥系统及公钥方案时，可以达成以下三个功能。
The first one is for encryption and decryption.
第一个用于加密和解密。
So that means the sender can encrypt a message with a recipient's public key, right?
这意味着发件人可以用接收者的公钥加密信息，对吗？
So that means the generated message Y can be transmitted in a public channel.
这意味着生成的消息 Y 可以在公共渠道中传输。
So this Y equals original message, or we call it to be C subtext, equals N to the E mod N.
因此，这个 Y 代表原始信息，或称为 C 子文本，等于 N 的 E 模 N。
So this is the encryption process.
这就是加密过程，简单来说。
We get the subtext and only the receiver with a private key can do the decryption.
我们获取到的是隐含信息，只有持有私钥的接收者才能进行解密。这句话经过润色，使其在简体中文中更加自然易懂。
So this is the encryption, decryption.
这就是加密和解密的过程。
Or the sender can sign a message with its private key.
发件人可以用自己的私钥对消息进行签名。这样的表述更符合中文的表达习惯。
We say this signature will be generated by M to the D mod N.
我们说这个签名将由 M 模 N 的 D 次幂生成。
Okay, you generate your signature and signature can be verified by receiver using your public key.
好的，您生成您的签名，接收者可以使用您的公钥进行验证。
Of course, we can use the public key scheme to do the key exchange.
当然可以，我们可以采用公钥方案进行密钥交换，这样更自然易懂。
Just like two sides can cooperate to exchange a session key, KAB, right?
就像两个部分可以合作交换一个会话密钥，KAB，对吗？
KAB in the Diffie-Hellman algorithm.
在 Diffie-Hellman 算法中，存在 KAB。
So both sides will get a key KAB equals G AB mod P, okay?
因此，双方都会得到一个密钥 KAB，等于 GAB 模 P，可以吗？
So Alice and Bob can locally choose the private data A and B.
因此，Alice 和 Bob 可以在本地选择私有数据 A 和 B。这样表达更为自然和易懂。
After some data exchange, they will locally get the same key KAB.
经过数据交换后，他们本地将获得相同的密钥 KAB。
This key KAB can be used for future message encryption in the symmetric encryption algorithm.
此密钥 KAB 可用于未来消息在对称加密算法中的加密。
Some public key algorithms are suitable for all three applications.
一些公钥算法适用于所有三种应用，表述更为自然易懂。
Some can be used for only one or two.
有些物品只能使用一次或两次，表达更为自然。
So RSA can be used for all three, right?
所以 RSA 可以用于这三个用途，对吗？
Encryption, decryption, digital signature.
加密、解密和数字签名。
So this is like a message to the E.
这就像是对 E 发的一条信息。
Digital signature can be generated by message to the D and key exchange.
数字签名可以通过向 D 发送消息并交换密钥来生成。
Key exchange means will the M to C to M, this M can be regarded as a key, okay?
密钥交换是指 M 到 C 再到 M 的过程，这里的 M 可以被视为一个密钥，好吗？
So both sender, receiver, they know the M to be the key to be used by both sides.
因此，发送方和接收方都知道 M 是双方需要使用的密钥。
Elliptic curve, similarly, well, this one requires some mathematical background.
椭圆曲线，嗯，这个需要一定的数学知识背景。
Well, so we don't talk about it.
好吧，我们就不提那件事了。
Elliptic curve is more efficient compared to the RSA.
椭圆曲线相对于 RSA 来说更加高效。
More efficient.
更高效（更自然、更易理解的表达）。
Now RSA, so they can achieve all three functions.
现在有了 RSA，他们能够实现所有三个功能。
Elliptic curve, this kind of public key scheme.
椭圆曲线，这是一种公钥方案。
The Diffie-Hellman is used only for DH, is only used for key exchange.
Diffie-Hellman 算法仅用于密钥交换，仅此一项功能。
And DSS is digital signature standard.
DSS 是数字签名标准，这是一个数字签名标准。
So this one is proposed by the United States.
这个是由美国提出的，表述更为自然。
This one is used only for digital signature generation and verification.
这个仅用于数字签名的生成与验证。
So this is a digital signature standard.
这是一种数字签名标准。
For the public key, this kind of scheme, it has some requirements.
对于公钥，这种方案有一些具体要求。
The public key algorithms must fulfill the following three requirements.
公钥算法必须满足以下三个基本要求。
The first requirement means that, well, it is computationally easy for party B to generate a pair of keys, right?
第一个要求的意思是，乙方生成一对密钥在计算上很简单，对吧？
To generate the key is not difficult.
生成密钥其实并不难。
So public key, like in RSA algorithm, where public key
如 RSA 算法中的公钥，这里的公钥是指
E and N, so we know the process, right? Once we know N equals P times Q, then we know phi N.
E 和 N，所以我们知道这个过程，对吧？一旦我们知道 N 等于 P 乘以 Q，那么我们就知道φN。这个翻译更加自然和易懂。
So from phi N we choose E, then we are able to calculate D easily.
因此，从 phi N 中选取 E，这样我们就能轻松计算出 D。
So D is a private key.
因此，D 是一个私钥。
So this process is not difficult. So once you have very large P and Q, two prime numbers,
这个过程并不复杂。所以一旦你拥有了非常大的质数 P 和 Q，那么...
then you can follow this process to generate the public key and the private key.
您可以按照以下步骤生成公钥和私钥（优化版）：
It is also computationally easy for sender A knowing the public key and the message to be encrypted to generate the corresponding subtext.
发送者 A 只要知道公钥和待加密的消息，生成相应的子文本在计算上就非常简单。
So C equals M to the E mod N. This is not that difficult.
因此，C 等于 M 的 E 次方对 N 取模。这并不复杂。
And also for the receiver B to do the decryption, this process is not difficult.
为了接收者 B 解密，这个过程并不复杂。
So that means to calculate M equals C to the D mod N, well, this is computationally achievable.
这意味着计算 M 等于 C 的 D 模 N，嗯，这在计算上是可行的。
However, it is computationally infeasible that for an adversary knowing the public key from E and N to determine the private key,
然而，敌手仅凭 E 和 N 的公钥无法计算出私钥，这在计算上是不切实际的，翻译如下：然而，仅凭 E 和 N 的公钥无法计算出私钥，这在计算上是不切实际的
this is infeasible.
这根本行不通。
Well, the only way is to derive the private key is you should guess N equals the product of P and Q.
好吧，获取私钥的唯一途径是猜测 N 等于 P 和 Q 的乘积。
How to get this P and Q? Well, this is infeasible at this moment.
如何得到这个 P 和 Q 呢？目前还无法实现。
So we can choose P and Q to be very large.
因此，我们可以选择 P 和 Q 的值非常大。这样表达更自然、易懂。
And also for an adversary, it is computationally infeasible from public key and subtext
对于对手而言，从公钥和暗文中进行计算是不可行的
to recover the original message M.
恢复原始消息 M（更自然、更易理解的翻译）
Because original message M equals C to the D mod N. Without this D, you cannot derive the original message M.
因为原始消息 M 等于 C 模 N。没有这个 D，就无法推导出原始消息 M。
Without D, you cannot get the original message M.
没有 D，就无法获取原始消息 M。
Well, in the public key scheme, the two keys can be applied in other order.
好的，在公钥体系中，这两个密钥可以按照不同的顺序使用。
Well, we can do the encryption like M to the D mod N or M to the C mod N.
好的，我们可以像 M 模 N 的 D 次方或 C 次方那样进行加密。这样的表述更符合中文的表达习惯。
So the second line means we want to achieve secrecy, confidentiality.
因此，第二行表示我们希望实现保密和机密性。
Secrecy. The first line means we want to achieve the signature authentication.
保密性。第一行表示我们希望实现签名认证功能。
Use your private key where you can generate your signature.
在您能够生成签名的地方使用您的私钥。
Use your public key where you can conceal your message M.
在您能够隐藏消息 M 的地方，请使用您的公钥。
So in this design, in this RSA algorithm, we call it.
在这个设计方案中，我们将其称为 RSA 算法。
So in this RSA algorithm, in the encryption-decryption process, we say, well, in fact, it provides some trapped one-way function.
在这个 RSA 算法中，加密解密过程中，实际上提供了一些具有陷门特性的单向函数。
First, we look at the meaning of one-way function.
首先，我们来探讨一下单射函数的含义。
So a one-way function means this function maps a domain into a range.
因此，单射函数是指这样一个函数，它将一个域映射到一个值域。
So from domain X, capital X, to a range Y. So that means it defines a mapping.
从域名 X，首字母大写的 X，到范围 Y。这表示它定义了一个映射关系。
A mapping from X to Y.
X 到 Y 的映射。
This is a function. A mapping from X to Y.
这是一个函数。X 到 Y 的映射关系。
So this function, given an input, given an input X belong to X.
因此，这个函数接受一个输入，即输入 X 属于 X。
So FX equals some Y. And this small y belong to the range.
因此，FX 等于某个 Y。这个小 y 位于该范围内。
From an X, we have a unique Y.
从 X 出发，我们拥有一个独特的 Y。
So this one-way means, well, from X to Y, it is this direction. It is easy.
这意味着，从 X 到 Y 的方向，很简单。
From X, given the input, we follow the function calculation. We get a Y. It is easy.
从 X 出发，根据输入，我们遵循函数计算过程。得到一个 Y。这很简单。
However, the inverse way is impossible.
然而，反过来是不行的。
So from Y to get the original X, this is infeasible. Not possible.
因此，从 Y 到获取原始 X 是不可行的，这是不可能实现的。
So we can see for the hash function, like the MD5, the SHA256.
我们可以看到，例如 MD5、SHA256 这样的哈希函数。
From the input X to the SHA256, with input X, we get its output, H.
从输入 X 到 SHA256 算法，输入 X 得到其输出 H。
This is easy. However, from H, if we want to guess what's the original input X, this is not possible.
这很简单。但是，从 H 开始，想要猜测原始输入 X 是什么，就无从下手了。
Well, based on the one-way function, we have the trapdoor one-way function.
基于单射函数，我们得到了具有陷阱门的单射函数。这个描述经过调整，使其在简体中文中更加自然易懂。
The trapdoor one-way function is a family of invertible function FK.
单向门函数族是一组可逆函数 FK，翻译得更加自然和易于理解。
Such that, well, with a K and with X input, we calculate the Y. It is easy.
嗯，输入 K 和 X，我们计算 Y，这很简单。
And also, with Y and the K, we get its inverse, reverse way. In the reverse way, we get original X. It is also easy.
“而且，加上 Y 和 K，我们得到它的逆，即反向方式。在反向方式中，我们就能得到原始的 X。这也很简单。”
However, if we don't know the K, well, to calculate the original input X, it is infeasible.
然而，若不知 K 值，计算原始输入 X 便无法进行。
So that means just like in our RSA algorithm, we have from, well, with the original message M,
这意味着正如我们在 RSA 算法中所做的那样，我们从原始消息 M 出发，
and we use the public key E, we use public key E, we mod N, we get the C. So this is easy.
我们使用公钥 E，对 N 取模得到 C，这个过程很简单。
We see C is Y, right? And once we have the D, we mod N, we get M. This is easy.
我们看到 C 对应 Y，对吧？一旦我们得到 D，对 N 取模后，就得到 M。这很简单。
However, without D, we send N to get M and no D, this is impossible.
然而，如果没有 D，我们发送 N 去获取 M，那就无法实现。
That means the D is a key K here. No D to get back the original message M, this is infeasible.
这意味着 D 是这里的密钥 K。没有 D 就无法恢复原始消息 M，这是行不通的。
So that means a practical public key scheme depends on a suitable trapdoor one-way function.
这意味着一个实用的公钥方案依赖于一个合适的门限单向函数，这样的表述更为自然易懂。
We should have the public key to do the decryption such that we can get the original message M from the self-text C.
我们需要拥有公钥以执行解密操作，从而从自文本 C 中提取原始消息 M。
Okay, we can see for the RSA algorithm, before the application of the public key crypto system, each participant must generate a pair of keys.
好的，在应用公钥加密系统之前，我们可以看到，每个参与者都需要生成一对密钥。
This pair of keys is E and D, right? E is a public key, D is a corresponding private key.
这对密钥是 E 和 D，对吧？E 是公钥，D 是相应的私钥。
To generate E and D, first we should choose two prime numbers, P and Q, secretly.
首先应秘密选择两个质数 P 和 Q，以生成 E 和 D。
You cannot disclose these two big numbers, otherwise people will generate your private key easily.
您不能泄露这两个重要数字，否则别人很容易就能推导出您的私钥。
So once you choose P and Q, normally you will select E and then you will calculate D as your private key.
因此，选择 P 和 Q 后，通常会选择 E，然后计算 D 作为您的私钥。
So because the value N equals P times Q will be, this N will be known to any potential adversary.
因此，由于 N 的值等于 P 乘以 Q，任何可能的对手都会知道这个 N。
The primes must be chosen from a sufficiently large set. So primes P, Q, you should choose these two to be very large, right?
素数必须从足够大的集合中选择。因此，素数 P 和 Q，您应该选择这两个数非常大，没错吧？
Okay, the method used for finding large primes, well, this method should be reasonably efficient.
好吧，寻找大质数所用的方法，嗯，这个方法应该效率很高。
To attack the RSA algorithm, we called this problem is a factoring problem.
为了攻击 RSA 算法，我们将其称为分解问题，这个问题旨在攻击 RSA 算法。
The reason is because once you can factor N into its two prime factors P and Q, so once you can get N equals P times Q,
原因在于，一旦你能够将 N 分解为它的两个质数因子 P 和 Q，一旦你能够得到 N 等于 P 乘以 Q，
then you will be able to calculate its corresponding potential function phi, right?
你就能计算出其对应的势函数φ了，对吧？
Once you can do that factorization, just like suppose N equals 1, 1, 9, so what's P and Q?
一旦你能完成这个因式分解，假设 N 等于 1、1、9，那么 P 和 Q 分别是多少？
P equals Q equals
P 等于 Q 等于
Okay, 7, 17, right? So then, well, because this number is very small, right?
好的，7，17，对吧？那么，嗯，这个数字实在太小了，对吧？
You can do the factorization quickly and then you'll be able to calculate the phi to be 96, right?
你可以快速进行因式分解，然后就能计算出 phi 为 96，对吧？（更自然、更易理解的翻译）
In our previous example, and then you will be able to suppose E is any number.
在我们之前的例子中，然后你可以假设 E 是任意一个数。
Can E be like, suppose E is 7, right?
假设 E 等于 7，对吗？
Can we choose E to be 10?
我们能否选择 E 为 10？
Not possible, why not?
不可能，为何如此？
Not really prime to phi, right?
真的跟 phi 不太搭，对吧？
So when you guarantee that DCT E and phi should be 1, so this one is not okay.
当你确保 DCT E 和 phi 值应为 1 时，这个就不对了。
Saving is fine. Well, given we know phi N, we know E, we will be able to generate the D.
储蓄没问题。既然已知 phi N，那么 E 也就知道了，我们就能生成 D。
So D equals actually is coming to
实际上，D 正在到来
So D is E must 1 mod phi N.
因此，D 是 E 模φN 等于 1。
To get the modular inverse value, we can use the extended Euclidean algorithm, but we can quickly calculate D from E and phi.
要获取模逆值，我们可以使用扩展欧几里得算法，但我们可以快速从 E 和φ计算出 D，翻译更加自然流畅。
So once we can do the factorization problem, we can solve the factorization of N and E is null.
因此，一旦我们解决了因式分解问题，就能解决 N 的因式分解问题，而 E 为空的情况。
So we will be able to calculate the private key D.
因此，我们将能够计算出私钥 D。
And we can see the history to do this factorization problem, the challenge.
我们可以回顾进行这个因式分解问题的历史，挑战之处。
In December 2000 online, well, we can factor rising the N.
2000 年 12 月在线时，嗯，我们可以考虑提升 N 的值。
So this N is the number of bits.
这里的 N 代表比特数。
To be 768 bits, corresponds to the number of decimal digits to be 232 decimal digits.
要成为 768 位，相当于 232 个十进制数字的位数。
The recent progress is in 2020.
近期进展发生在 2020 年。
Well, a group of people showed that we are able to factorize big N with the 829 bits.
嗯，一群人证明了我们能够将 829 位的 N 大数分解成质因数。这个翻译更加自然和易于理解。
The length for N to be over 800 is not secure anymore.
N 的长度超过 800 不再安全，这样的设置已经不够安全了。
So it is suggested that we should at least choose the N to be 1 or 24 bits today.
今天至少应选择 1 或 24 位的 N
Or to be more secure, to be 2 or 48 bits.
更安全地讲，是 2 位或 48 位。
For your N to generate your public key and private key in your application.
为您的 N 生成您应用程序中的公钥和私钥。
Okay, so let's have an overview about the encryption.
好的，那么我们先来了解一下加密的基本情况。
So we can use either the symmetric encryption.
我们可以采用对称加密方式。
So symmetric encryption means we assume we can achieve confidentiality.
对称加密意味着我们假设能够实现保密性。这样的表述更加自然易懂。
That means the message will be kept to be a secret.
这意味着这条消息将被严格保密。
Will only be known by the sender and the receiver.
只会为发送者和接收者所知。这句话听起来略显生硬，可以调整为：“只有发送者和接收者知晓。”这样更符合中文的表达习惯。
Because both the sender and the receiver, they have the key K.
因为发送者和接收者都拥有密钥 K。
And this key K can be used in both the encryption and the decryption algorithm, like the AES algorithm.
这把密钥 K 可用于加密和解密算法，例如 AES 算法。这样的表述在中文中更为自然和易于理解。
So in this symmetric scheme, we can achieve the message confidentiality.
在这个对称方案中，我们能够实现消息的保密性。
Not known by others.
他人不清楚
So the message cannot be known by others.
因此，别人无法得知这条信息。
If we apply the public key encryption,
如果我们使用公钥加密，
Once we use the public key of the receiver B,
当我们使用接收者 B 的公钥时，
And then we can achieve the message confidentiality.
然后我们就能实现消息的保密性。
The reason is because only the receiver can do the decryption.
原因在于只有接收者才能进行解密操作。
Or we can use AES public key to do the encryption.
我们可以采用 AES 公钥进行加密，这样更自然易懂。
Then we can generate the signature along with the message.
我们可以生成消息和签名，这样更自然易懂。
So this signature will be verified by the receiver B.
因此，这个签名将由接收者 B 进行验证。
So B will use the sender's public key for verification.
B 将使用发送者的公钥进行验证，这样的表述更为自然易懂。
So B as the receiver will guarantee that the message is really from Alice.
因此，作为接收者的 B 将确保消息确实来自 Alice。
Because the B is using Alice's public key to do the decryption.
因为 B 使用 Alice 的公钥进行解密。
Of course, we can use both the private key and public key at both the sender side and the receiver side.
当然，发送方和接收方都可以使用私钥和公钥。这样的表述更自然、易懂。
So private key for signature generation and public key for the message confidentiality.
用于签名生成的私钥，以及用于保障消息保密性的公钥。
To achieve message confidentiality, to guarantee the message is encrypted and not known by others.
为了确保消息的机密性，保证消息加密且不被他人所知。
So in the decryption side, the receiver side, we can do the decryption.
在解密方面，接收方可以进行解密操作。
First use the receiver's private key to do the decryption and then to do the verification.
首先使用接收者的私钥进行解密，然后进行验证。（已优化，使翻译更自然易懂）
So public key of Alice to do the signature verification.
爱丽丝的公钥用于进行签名验证。
Authentication and signature actually should be the same meaning.
认证和签名本应具有相同的意义。
We verify your signature will guarantee this real sender.
我们将验证您的签名，以确保这是真正的发件人。
So we guarantee this real sender.
我们确保这是真正的发件人。
The real sender means this authentication will authorize.
真实发件人表示，这项认证将获得授权。
You're authorized because you can provide a correct signature.
您有权限，因为您能提供正确的签名。（经过优化，使翻译更加自然易懂）
So then we finish our lecture three.
然后我们结束了第三讲的内容。
And we have the TECOM exercises for your practice.
我们为您准备了 TECOM 练习，方便您进行练习。
So exercise four is for RSA and exercise five is for Diffie-Hellman algorithm.
第四题是 RSA 算法，第五题是迪菲-赫尔曼密钥交换算法。
OK, so we finish and let's have a stop, have a break, 10 minutes.
好的，我们结束休息一下，休息 10 分钟。
OK, then after break, we continue with lecture four.
那么，休息一下后，我们继续进行第四讲的学习。
Thank you.
谢谢您。